Robert Patterson Collection of Textile Related Photographs 6865 P
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Robert Patterson Collection of Textile Related Photographs
1965
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Robert Patterson
American Textile History Museum
6865 P
1 folders
1 file folder
Gelatin silver print, photographs.
Photographs of Knowles Loom Works and Crompton & Knowles Loom Works machinery.
10068214
Scope and Contents
Images depict several types of either the Knowles Loom Works or the Crompton & Knowles Loom Works textile machinery. These particular machines were probably built or sold in England by Hutchinson, Hollingworth & Company, Ltd. All machinery photographs are attributed to Robert Patterson, Lancashire, England, but are stamped on the back, "Castle Museum York, The Folk Museum of Yorkshire Life." Also includes five photographs of weaver's cottages at the York Castle Museum, York, England. These photographs are also stamped "Castle Museum York, The Folk Museum of Yorkshire Life" on the back.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Custodial History
American Textile History Museum Collection, gift of Robert Patterson
Related Materials
Related Collections: 6584 G: Ralph Huey Collection of Crompton & Knowles Graphics 6584 P: Ralph Huey Collection of Crompton & Knowles Photographs 6585/001: Crompton & Knowles General Records 6585 G: Crompton & Knowles Graphics 6585 P: Crompton & Knowles Photographs
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives 227 Ives Hall Tower Road Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheelref@cornell.edu https://catherwood.library.cornell.edu/kheel/
Compiled by:
R. Miles, October 18, 2017
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, December 06, 2017
Looms; Moquette; Textile machinery; Textile machinery industry; Weaving; Lancashire (England); York (England); Patterson, Robert; Crompton & Knowles Loom Works; Hutchinson, Hollingworth & Co.; Knowles Loom Works; York Castle Museum; American Textile History Museum
10068214
- York Castle Museum Photographs, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Crompton & Knowles tappet [cam] loom, ATHM# 0000.385.1, 1965; black and white photograph; 10 x 15.5 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Gelatin silver print snapshot. Image depicts a Crompton & Knowles tappet loom (tappet is the British term for cam) in Lancashire, England, with a 4 by 1 shuttle box, and 40" reed space. Maker's name is clearly painted, which would place the manufacture of this loom after 1897, when the Crompton Loom Works and the Knowles Loom Works merged into Crompton & Knowles Loom Works.
  - Knowles Loom Works dobby loom, ATHM# 0000.385.2, 1965; black and white photograph; 10 x 15.25 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print snapshot. Image depicts a Knowles Loom Works dobby loom in Lancashire, England, with a 4 by 1 shuttle box and 30" reed space. Patents dated 1886 and 1887. Maker's name is clearly painted, which would place the manufacture of this loom between 1887 and 1897, when the Crompton Loom Works and the Knowles Loom Works merged into Crompton & Knowles Loom Works.
  - Knowles Loom Works dobby loom, ATHM# 0000.375.3, 1965; black and white photograph; 15.5 x 10 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print snapshot. Image depicts a Knowles Loom Works dobby loom (in the center) in Lancashire, England, with a 4 by 1 shuttle box and 40" reed space with crossing-motion reed (possibly for curtain weaving?). Maker's name is indistinct, but the name Knowles Loom Works would place the manufacture of this loom before 1897, when the Crompton Loom Works and the Knowles Loom Works merged into Crompton & Knowles Loom Works. See item 5 in this folder for a view of this loom from the opposite angle.
  - Dobby looms, ATHM# 0000.385.4, 1965; black and white photograph; 15.75 x 10.25 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print snapshot. Image depicts several dobby looms in Lancashire, England. Loom in the center, partially obscured by post, is a Knowles Loom Works dobby loom; see item 3 in this folder. Loom partially seen in the right foreground has no maker's name visible, but may be a Crompton & Knowles knife loom.
  - Another view of Knowles Loom Works dobby loom, ATHM# 0000.385.5, 1965; black and white photograph; 15.25 x 10.25 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print snapshot. Image depicts a Knowles Loom Works dobby loom in Lancashire, England, with a 4 by 1 shuttle box and 40" reed space with crossing-motion reed (possibly for curtain weaving?). See item 3 in this folder for a view of this loom from the opposite angle. Maker's name is indistinct, but the name Knowles Loom Works would place the manufacture of this loom before 1897, when the Crompton Loom Works and the Knowles Loom Works merged into Crompton & Knowles.
  - Crompton & Knowles knife-loom, ATHM# 0000.385.6, 1965; black and white photograph; 15.75 x 10 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print snapshot. Image depicts a knife-loom in Lancashire, England, for cut moquette weaving. Moquette can be any of several varieties of warp pile fabrics commonly made with the pile of wool or mohair and the ground of cotton; in this case the pile was cut rather than looped. Usually made in upholstery weight and construction, but sometimes applied to certain carpet styles. No maker's name visible, but possibly a Crompton & Knowles loom. A Crompton & Knowles tappet (cam) loom is on the right. The name Crompton & Knowles would place the manufacture of these looms after 1897, when the Crompton Loom Works and the Knowles Loom Works merged into Crompton & Knowles Loom Works.
  - Knowles dobby loom with Knowles box motion, ATHM# 0000.385.7, 1965; black and white photograph; 10 x 15.25 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print snapshot. Image depicts what is probably a Knowles dobby loom in Lancashire, England, with a 4 by 4 shuttle box and 34" reed space. No maker's name visible, but has a Knowles original dobby and a Knowles box motion. Unclear if this loom was manufactured before or after 1897 when the Crompton Loom Works and the Knowles Loom Works merged into Crompton & Knowles Loom Works.
  - Knowles Loom Works tappet [cam] loom, ATHM# 0000.385.8, 1965; black and white photograph; 10 x 15.25 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print snapsho. Image depicts a Knowles Loom Works tappet loom (tappet is the British term for cam) with low dobby for boxes only in Lancashire, England, with a 6 by 1 shuttle box and 33" reed space. Maker's name cast into frame and very clear, which would place the manufacture of this loom before 1897 when the Crompton Loom Works and the Knowles Loom Works merged into Crompton & Knowles.
  - Tappet [cam] and dobby looms, ATHM# 0000.385.9, 1965; black and white photograph; 15.25 x 10.25 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print snapshot. Image depicts several looms in Lancashire, England. One (in the right foreground) has no maker's name visible and is probably French. The second (in the center) is a Knowles Loom Works tappet (the British term for cam) loom. The other two are a dobby looms with no maker's name visible, and possibly a Knowles tappet loom, both with single shuttle boxes.
  - Tappet [cam] and dobby looms, ATHM# 0000.385.10, 1965; black and white photograph; 15.5 x 10 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print snapshot. Image depicts three looms in Lancashire, England. Front to back, they are a possible Crompton & Knowles tappet (the British term for cam) loom, with a box dobby and 34" reed space; a possible Crompton & Knowles dobby loom, with 30" reed space, probably a silk loom; and a definite Crompton & Knowles loom with patent dates 1888 to July 30, 1897. The first two have no maker's name visible but are thought to be Crompton & Knowles. Manufactured in 1897 or later, as the Crompton Loom Works and the Knowles Loom Works merged in 1897 to form Crompton & Knowles Loom Works.
  - Weaver's cottages, ATHM# 0000.385.11, 1965; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Snapshot. York Castle Museum, York, England
  - Weaver's cottages, ATHM# 0000.385.12, 1965; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Weaver's cottages, ATHM# 0000.385.13, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Weaver's cottages, ATHM# 0000.385.14, 1965; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Weaver's cottages, ATHM# 0000.385.15, 1965; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)